<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-07T10:47:05+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">A life that made sense</title><subtitle>My family and I took a road less traveled. This blog will be a journal concerning our new life in France. I hope to share some fun engineering projects also along the way.</subtitle><author><name>Mike Hinkle</name></author><entry><title type="html">Broken virtual environments: Why it happened and how I should have prevented it</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/linux/update/python/venv/broken/prevention/2021/07/06/fixing_broken_venv.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Broken virtual environments: Why it happened and how I should have prevented it" /><published>2021-07-06T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-07-06T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/linux/update/python/venv/broken/prevention/2021/07/06/fixing_broken_venv</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/linux/update/python/venv/broken/prevention/2021/07/06/fixing_broken_venv.html">&lt;p&gt;Approximately 3-4 days ago, I updated my Linux box (&lt;strong&gt;Pop!_OS&lt;/strong&gt; version 20.10 -&amp;gt; 21.04). 
I have run Linux long enough to know that there could be unintended issues during
these major version updates. My first defense against possible headaches is to wait for
a few days and hope others find the bugs, report them and everything gets ironed out quickly.
Years ago I was not as cautious :see_no_evil:, but I no longer have the luxury of time to bang my head
into a desk for days and slog through issues or re-compile kernels. I just play it safe now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The good news is that despite a drastic change to the Pop!_OS desktop environment
(from &lt;strong&gt;GNOME 3.38.4&lt;/strong&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;COSMIC&lt;/strong&gt;), the update and upgrade went very smoothly. The new DE
is an improvement on GNOME, my system is very responsive, the stars all aligned and
everything is perfect. Kudos to the system76 team :thumbsup:. But.. Not everything
was perfect…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-exactly-was-the-problem&quot;&gt;What exactly was the problem?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me begin by saying that my issue has nothing to do with my updated OS. I decided
yesterday that I wanted to update a Heroku application which lives in a local repository
on my now updated workstation. This application was written in Python and the interpreter executed within a 
virtual environment (venv). Virtual environments should be self contained, correct? 
Sounds safe right :skull:? What happened was that the OS upgrade replaced my pre-existing system python (3.8) with
a newer python version (3.9). Had I sourced a standalone python install when creating the
virtual environment, or had the OS just switched PYTHON_TARGETS, then I would not be
writing this right now. I had created the venv like so for this particular Heroku application:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;soitgoes@pop-os:~$ python3 -m venv venv&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above command created said virtual environment inside a directory called venv with a symbolic link
pointing from the venv interpreter to my system python interpreter @ /usr/bin/python3.8 which no longer existed :disappointed::&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;lrwxrwxrwx 1 soitgoes soitgoes    6 Jun 17 21:38 python3.8 -&amp;gt; python&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At my previous work, I had many python versions installed on a dev mount to avoid this very issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;how-to-fix-the-issue-and-my-steps-moving-forward-&quot;&gt;How to fix the issue and my steps moving forward …&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Install a standalone development python which lives seperately and isolated from my system python. This
would avoid the pain I am enduring now when my system is updated again with a new python install. 
I have no excuse for dropping the ball like this but it is what it is. Lesson learned.
Steps to remedy the situation, starting with that isolated python install:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Download desired python version &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ wget https://www.python.org/ftp/python/3.8.11/Python-3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Uncompress the python version   &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ tar -xzvf Python-3.8.11.tgz&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Change into directory           &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ cd Python-3.8.11/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Configure with target location  &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ ./configure --prefix=/home/soitgoes/python-3.8.11&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Compile and build               &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ make&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Test build                      &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ make test&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Install python to target location  &lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ make altinstall&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see that the above steps were successful by executing the newly installed
interpreter which was specified in my target location above (/home/soitgoes/python-3.8.11)
:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;soitgoes@pop-os:~$ ~/python-3.8.11/bin/python3.8&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And voilà… The REPL (&lt;strong&gt;R&lt;/strong&gt;ead, &lt;strong&gt;E&lt;/strong&gt;valuate, &lt;strong&gt;P&lt;/strong&gt;rint, &lt;strong&gt;L&lt;/strong&gt;oop) prompt appears reflecting
my desired version:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Python 3.8.11 (default, Jul  6 2021, 22:44:39)
[GCC 10.3.0] on linux
Type &quot;help&quot;, &quot;copyright&quot;, &quot;credits&quot; or &quot;license&quot; for more information.
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My system python has been unchanged and I can verify this very easily:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;soitgoes@pop-os:~$ which python3
/usr/bin/python3
soitgoes@pop-os:~$ python3
Python 3.9.5 (default, May 11 2021, 08:20:37)
[GCC 10.3.0] on linux
Type &quot;help&quot;, &quot;copyright&quot;, &quot;credits&quot; or &quot;license&quot; for more information.
&amp;gt;&amp;gt;&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Please notice the versioning differences. The next step in this process will be to
rebuild the symbolic links in the affected virtual environment. Please make note that
the python3 symlink points to the system /usr/bin/python3 (which is the issue since it
is now python 3.9 rather than 3.8). The other symlinks just chain all the python 
aliases together: python -&amp;gt; python3 which I just mentioned points to the system python
install. Finally, the last link is python3.9 -&amp;gt; python3 again:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;lrwxrwxrwx 1 soitgoes soitgoes    7 Jul  4 22:58 python -&amp;gt; python3
lrwxrwxrwx 1 soitgoes soitgoes   16 Jul  4 22:58 python3 -&amp;gt; /usr/bin/python3
lrwxrwxrwx 1 soitgoes soitgoes    7 Jul  4 22:58 python3.9 -&amp;gt; python3
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These soft links need to be re-directed to my newly built and installed python which
is now located in my home directory. I can do this simply by changing into the affected
venv/bin/ directory where the symlinks are present and then:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-plaintext highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;$ ln -sf /home/soitgoes/python-3.8.11/bin/python3.8 python3&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The symlinks are now corrected. When activating the previously affected venv, and
running the python interpreter I am greeted with version 3.8.11 rather than 3.9.5.
My application will again run without the need of rebuilding all of my dependencies.
Since this is fixed and it is getting late, I will need to actually do what I set out
to do initially (update my Heroku app) later. Enough problems solved for one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The moral of the story is to ensure you seperate your system dependencies from your
development dependencies. No sense in muddying the waters and causing unnecessary
headaches.&lt;/strong&gt; :heavy_check_mark:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The mind is not a vessel to be filled, but a fire to be kindled.
&lt;em&gt;― Plutarch&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Hinkle</name></author><category term="linux" /><category term="update" /><category term="python" /><category term="venv" /><category term="broken" /><category term="prevention" /><summary type="html">Approximately 3-4 days ago, I updated my Linux box (Pop!_OS version 20.10 -&amp;gt; 21.04). I have run Linux long enough to know that there could be unintended issues during these major version updates. My first defense against possible headaches is to wait for a few days and hope others find the bugs, report them and everything gets ironed out quickly. Years ago I was not as cautious :see_no_evil:, but I no longer have the luxury of time to bang my head into a desk for days and slog through issues or re-compile kernels. I just play it safe now.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Initial observations while settling in</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/france/blog/careers/ee/2021/06/26/initial_observations.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Initial observations while settling in" /><published>2021-06-26T17:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-26T17:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/france/blog/careers/ee/2021/06/26/initial_observations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/france/blog/careers/ee/2021/06/26/initial_observations.html">&lt;p&gt;I have begun applying for jobs. Perhaps I am being un-realistic considering
I am a beginner in the French language. I could not imagine finding a job in
the states and not speaking English. :crossed_fingers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;some-observations-&quot;&gt;Some observations …&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first observation is that most positions in the fields I am looking for are
looking for Master’s or PHd’s. I guess when university doesn’t cost $100k for
an undergraduate degree :moneybag:, there is more motivation to go a step further. I find myself
regretting not sticking it out for my Master’s but that ship has sailed. At least
I have experience in industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My second observation is that Electrical Engineering degrees here do not translate
to the same studies in the US. I could be wrong and I will have a better perspective
on this very shortly. I have noticed quite a bit of variation in EE degrees in the US, 
too. I have friends which never studied transistors at their schools. We were drowned in
small signal models, large signal models, BJT’s, MOSFET’s, etc.. After long
discussions with my wife in the past, my understanding is that the French University
system is, for the most part, standardized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Due to the second observation above :point_up:, there will probably be some
ambiguity for potential employers. I am attempting to find a career in big data,
data science, data engineering, analytics, web development, etc.. Not sure if that
aligns even remotely with what their EE’s learn at University, but it is not a huge
leap from my past curriculum and studies. Only time will tell. It has only been
2 weeks since I set foot on French soil and I need to be patient and keep plugging away.
On the bright side, in the meantime, I can spend time with my family. I never would 
have had this much time with my children had we stayed in the US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Per aspera ad astra&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Hinkle</name></author><category term="france" /><category term="blog" /><category term="careers" /><category term="EE" /><summary type="html">I have begun applying for jobs. Perhaps I am being un-realistic considering I am a beginner in the French language. I could not imagine finding a job in the states and not speaking English. :crossed_fingers:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A new start in France</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/first/france/blog/careers/family/2021/06/21/new_start_in_france.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A new start in France" /><published>2021-06-21T16:01:00+02:00</published><updated>2021-06-21T16:01:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/first/france/blog/careers/family/2021/06/21/new_start_in_france</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/first/france/blog/careers/family/2021/06/21/new_start_in_france.html">&lt;p&gt;I will keep this short and sweet. I left corporate life in &lt;strong&gt;America&lt;/strong&gt; to move to my wife’s home country, &lt;strong&gt;France&lt;/strong&gt;. I had worked in the &lt;em&gt;semiconductor industry&lt;/em&gt; for about 4 years as 
an &lt;em&gt;engineer&lt;/em&gt; in various roles. My background at University was &lt;strong&gt;Electrical Engineering&lt;/strong&gt; with a concentration in microelectronics. My employer treated me well and finances were good. 
I had a real career. About 3.5 years ago my beautiful daughter was born. My wife and I were informed at our 20 week sonogram that there were issues. Our life has never been the same 
since.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been through plenty of hard times in my life, but to this day, seeing her struggles has really darkened my soul. We came to France so her and my son could be with family. We
came to France so they could be loved. We are only here on this earth for a brief moment and like &lt;em&gt;Bob Marley&lt;/em&gt; said so wonderfully:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“…life is worth much more than gold.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is my first blog entry. I promise that I will delve into some fun projects down the road. I am waiting until we purchase our house to nerd out on some &lt;strong&gt;IOT and pub-sub messaging
systems&lt;/strong&gt;. If you read this, thank you. :grin:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;display: inline-block;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/baby_girl_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; style=&quot;height: 300px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: inline-block;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/french_town_1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; style=&quot;height: 300px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;display: inline-block;&quot;&gt;
  &lt;img src=&quot;/assets/baby_boy_1.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;drawing&quot; style=&quot;height: 300px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mike Hinkle</name></author><category term="first" /><category term="france" /><category term="blog" /><category term="careers" /><category term="family" /><summary type="html">I will keep this short and sweet. I left corporate life in America to move to my wife’s home country, France. I had worked in the semiconductor industry for about 4 years as an engineer in various roles. My background at University was Electrical Engineering with a concentration in microelectronics. My employer treated me well and finances were good. I had a real career. About 3.5 years ago my beautiful daughter was born. My wife and I were informed at our 20 week sonogram that there were issues. Our life has never been the same since.</summary></entry></feed>